Theodore Roscoe Papers
Theodore Roscoe Papers
1871-1992
Roscoe, Theodore.
22.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American author of adventure and mystery stories and U.S. Navy historian (1906-1992). Collection includes correspondence, writings, and memorabilia. Correspondence (1926-1992) with editors, publishers, colleagues, fans, and the U.S. Department of the Navy. Writings -- fiction, non-fiction, notebooks, reviews, and scripts -- contains manuscript drafts, manuscripts, and published material, including examples of adventure and mystery stories written for pulp magazines and material relating to the history of the U.S. Navy. Memorabilia comprises financial material, printed material, and scrapbooks. Printed material consists of books owned by Roscoe, clippings about Roscoe or those which contained story ideas, publicity, and reviews. Many of the scrapbooks pertain to his writings on naval history.
149453
Biographical History
Theodore Roscoe was an American author of the "pulp" era, known for his adventure and mystery stories as well as naval history. In addition to books (both fiction and nonfiction), his stories appeared in magazines such as Adventure, Argosy, and Weird Tales.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Theodore Roscoe Papers comprises correspondence, writings, and memorabilia that span Roscoe's entire career.
Correspondence (Box 1) spans the years 1926 to 1992. Roscoe corresponded with editors, publishers, colleagues, fans, and the U.S. Department of the Navy.
Writings (Boxes 2-12) includes Roscoe's fiction and non-fiction as well as notebooks, reviews, and scripts. Fiction (Boxes 2-4) includes manuscript drafts, manuscripts, and some printed examples of his adventure and mystery stories, which were written for pulp magazines. Non-fiction (Boxes 4-10) contains manuscript drafts, manuscripts and published work, much of which pertains to the history of the U.S. Navy. Scripts (Box 10-12) include manuscript draft and manuscript dramatizations of some of Roscoe's fictional work.
Memorabilia (Boxes 12-13) comprises financial material, printed material, and scrapbooks. Printed material consists of books that were owned by Roscoe, clippings about Roscoe or those which contained Story ideas, publicity, and reviews. Many of the scrapbooks pertain to his writings an naval history.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Writings are arranged alphabetically by type and within that by title. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Historians; Military history; Popular culture; Literature -- American Fiction; Roscoe, Theodore.; United States. -- Navy -- History.; United States. -- Navy -- Submarine forces.; Adventure and adventurers in literature.; Adventure stories, American -- 20th century.; American fiction -- 20th century.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Detective and mystery stories, American -- 20th century.; Fiction -- Male authors -- United States -- 20th century.; Historians -- United States -- 20th century.; Naval history -- United States.; Naval history, Modern -- United States -- 20th century.; Popular literature -- United States.; War and literature -- United States -- 20th century.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Naval operations -- Submarine.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Naval operations -- American.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Galley proofs.; Histories.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Scripts (documents); Authors.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Theodore Roscoe, 1965, 1967. Gift of Mrs. Theodore Roscoe, 1992.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Biographical material, includes family history, genealogy (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1992 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Fiction
    - "Amusement Park", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Are the Anchors Really Aweigh?", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Barbecue", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Beauty and the Beast", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Bentfinger" Argosy, May 23, 1931 (Box 2)
    - "Betraying Black" The Clarion, Oct. 1922 (Oversize 1)
    - "Betraying Black" The Clarion, Nov. 8, 1922 (Oversize 1)
    - "Birthday Letter" The All Story Braille Magazine, Aug. 1944 (Oversize 1)
    - "Black-out", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Blueberry Pie", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Border Incident", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Bring 'Em Back Dead", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Brodie Takes a Steve", manuscripts (Box 2)
    - "Brother Death", manuscript (Box 2)
    - "The Buddhist Monk", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "The Buddhist Monk" Adventure, July 5, 1928 (Box 2)
    - "But '0o Was Shykspeare?", manuscripts (Box 2)
    - "Cal of the Corona" The Clarion, Apr. 26, 1922 (Oversize 1)
    - "The Case of the Incredible Messenger", manuscripts (Box 2)
    - "The Case of the Man Inside" Flynn's Detective Fiction, undated (Box 2)
    - "Checkered Retribution" Argosy, undated (Box 2)
    - "Cherchez la Femme", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Close Shave", ms. draft, unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Clune for President for Christ's Sake", ms draft (Box 2)
    - "Confidence", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Continuity for 'Hucksters' Strip: Synopsis", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Corday and the Seven League Boots", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Creeron Cracks Wise", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Creeron Cracks Wise" Argosy, Feb. 9, 1929 (Box 2)
    - "The Curse Kiss" Weird Tales (1 pulp, 1 photocopy), Feb. 1930 (Box 2)
    - "The Dance of the Seven Veils" Argosy, Oct. 19, 1929 (Box 2)
    - "The Dancing Death" Weird Tales (photocopy), Oct. 1928 (Box 2)
    - "Dark Tomorrow", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Dead Man's Answer", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Dead Man's Fist", ms. drafts (Box 2)
    - "Dead Man's Gold" Detective Fiction Weekly, June 4, 1932 (Box 2)
    - "Dead Mens Ears" Action Stories, Dec. 1928 (Box 2)
    - "Death Below Zero", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Death Cheaters" The Clarion, Mar. 9, 1922 (Oversize 1)
    - "Death Cheaters" The Clarion, Mar. 16, 1922 (Oversize 1)
    - "Death Comes to a New England Princess", research material, ms. drafts (Box 2)
    - "Death Doesn't Miss the Bus", ms. draft fragment (Box 2)
    - "Death Drums" Argosy, undated (Box 2)
    - "Death Song of Absinthe Devolle", manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Death Song of Absinthe Devolle" Argosy, undated (Box 2)
    - "Debauch on the Rhine", source material (Box 2)
    - "The Demon from Heaven", manuscript (Box 2)
    - "The Demon from Heaven" Air Adventures, Jan. 1929 (Box 2)
    - "Design for Murder", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Devil Dance" Action Stories, Nov. 1931 (Box 2)
    - "The Devil, Too, Has Wings", manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Dirge of the Nancy D." Argosy, Aug. 22, 1931 (Box 2)
    - "Don't Count Your Chickens", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Down Mexico Way", manuscript fragment (Box 2)
    - "The Ears of Donkey Daudette", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "The Education of John Edwards", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Erie Queen", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "The Eventful Day" The Clarion, Dec. 20, 1922 (Oversize 1)
    - "Farmer, Have You a Daughter Fair?", manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Fashion Note", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Fe Fi Fo Fum", manuscripts (Box 2)
    - "The Fight That Failed" The Clarion, Dec. 21, 1922 (Oversize 1)
    - "Foley of the Foreign Legion" Wide World Adventures, July 1, 1929 (Box 2)
    - "For They Shall See God", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Four Corners" Stories, ms. drafts (Box 2)
    - "The Four Horsemen of 1945", ms. drafts (Box 2)
    - "Frightened Lady", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Gambit" Complete Stories, Mar. 2, 1931 (Box 2)
    - "Garne Called on Account of Darkness", ms. drafts (Box 2)
    - "The Green-handled Dagger", ms. (Box 2)
    - "The Green-handled Dagger" Short Stories, undated (Box 2)
    - "Hard-boiled Cayhill's Christmas Eve Party", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Hard-boiled Cayhill's Christmas Eve Party" Argosy, Dec. 28, 1929 (Box 2)
    - "Here Are Your Police", manuscript (Box 2)
    - "His Honor is Missing" (working title: "Where Are You, Your Honor?"), ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "His Honor is Missing" Argosy, undated (Box 2)
    - "H.M.S. New York", ms. drafts (Box 2)
    - "Horror on the River", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "I Saw Him Die", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "I Will Repay" The Clarion, Oct. 19, 1921 (Oversize 1)
    - I'll Grind Their Bones, April 19, 1905 (Box 2)
    - "Imperfect Crime", ms. drafts (Box 2)
    - "In the Garden of Allah", manuscript (Box 2)
    - "In the Red Zone", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Jersey Devil", ms. draft, manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Ladies in Trouble", manuscript (Box 2)
    - "The Lady is Mysterious", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "The Lame, the Halt, and the Blind", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Lee's Lieutenant", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Leopard Teeth" Argosy, undated (Box 2)
    - "Letter from Anne", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Letter Out of History", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Liberty for Christmas" The Clarion, Dec. 21, 1921 (Oversize 1)
    - "Line-up", manuscript fragment (Box 2)
    - "Listen Tiger!", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "The Little Gold Dove of Gojjam" Argosy, undated (Box 2)
    - "Low Bridge", unpublished manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Luck", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Luck" Short Stories (2 pulp), undated (Box 2)
    - "Lucky Number", ms. draft (Box 2)
    - "Lure of the Islands", manuscript (Box 3)
    - "Lure of the Islands" Argosy, undated (Box 3)
    - "Mademoiselle Hideous", manuscript fragment (Box 3)
    - "The Man Who Died Twice" Flynn's Detective Fiction, undated (Box 3)
    - "The Man Who Hated Lincoln", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "The Man Who Went to Hell", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "The Man With the Bald Head", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "Manchuria", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "Manhunt in Tunisia" (working title: "Evening in Kairowain"), manuscript (Box 3)
    - "Manhunt in Tunisia" The Sergeant is a Jerk!, April 27, 1905 (Box 3)
    - "Marianne", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "Mary Had a Little Jam", ms. draft fragment (Box 3)
    - "A Matter of Life and Death", unpublished manuscript (Box 3)
    - "Mine Not to Reason Why", manuscripts (Box 3)
    - "Mister Mystery", unpublished manuscript (Box 3)
    - "Monkey See, Monkey Do", revisions and insertions (Box 3)
    - "Murder" Complete Stories, Mar. 1, 1929 (Box 3)
    - Murder on the Way, April 18, 1905 (Box 3)
    - "My Lady of Death" Flynn's Detective Fiction, undated (Box 3)
    - "The Napoleon Bonaparte Murder Case", research material, ms. drafts (Box 3)
    - "Natchez Trace", ms. drafts, unpublished manuscript fragments (Box 3)
    - "A Night in Honduras", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "Notes on Military Training", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "Octopus", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "Officer and a Gentleman", unpublished manuscripts (Box 3)
    - "The Old Boy", ms. draft (Box 3)
    - "Old Napoleon" Argosy (2 pulp, 1 photocopy), Dec. 21, 1929 (Box 3)
    - Only in New England (working title: "Murder by Gaslight"), ms. draft, master copy, galley proof (front matter) (Box 3)
    - "Our Scandalous Presidents", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Paragraph for the Arganotes", ms. drafts (Box 4)
    - "Passion is a Killer", unpublished manuscripts (Box 4)
    - "Patrol of the Skies" Air Stories, Apr. 1928 (Box 4)
    - "The Plane Fool" Air Stories, Apr. 1929 (Box 4)
    - "President Stories", manuscripts (Box 4)
    - "The Pushover Fight Stories", Mar. 1929 (Box 4)
    - "Quadruple Cross", unpublished manuscripts (Box 4)
    - "The Red Spectre", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "The Red Widow Murder Case", research material, ms. drafts, manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Reward" Action Stories, Mar. 1929 (Box 4)
    - "Right Answer", ms. draft (Box 4)
    - "The Ruby of Suratan Singh" Argosy, July 12, 1930 (Box 4)
    - "S is for Shark", manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Sailor of Fortune", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Salesmanship", unpublished manuscripts (Box 4)
    - "Scum of the Sea", ms. drafts (Box 4)
    - "Secret Cargo", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Seeing Eyes", ms. draft (Box 4)
    - "Seen and Heard", ms. drafts (Box 4)
    - "Senor Death", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Sentiment", unpublished manuscripts (Box 4)
    - "Seven for the Executioner", ms. drafts (Box 4)
    - "Seven Men", ms. draft (Box 4)
    - "Seven Men" Detective Fiction Weekly, Apr. 12 (Box 4)
    - "Shake Hands With Old Hickory", manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Sharp Sabres" Soldier Stories, Apr. 1929 (Box 4)
    - "Soldier of the Legion" Adventure Trails, Mar. 28 (Box 4)
    - "Spy With the Bald Head", corrections and insertions (Box 4)
    - "Star Death", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Stille Nacht", ms. draft (Box 4)
    - "Stories for 1946", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Submarine Girl", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Synthetic Crime", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "A Tale from the Twilight Zone", ms. drafts (Box 4)
    - "Terrible Lady", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Terror Chateau", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Thanksgiving -- 1634", manuscript (Box 4)
    - "They Also Serve", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "They Made Headlines: Sensational People of the Past", unpublished manuscripts (Box 4)
    - "Till Death Do Us Part", manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Till Death Do Us Part" Flynn's Detective Fiction, undated (Box 4)
    - "Too Bad About Mr. Denam", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Tower of Death" Action Stories (2 pulp), Sept. 1931 (Box 4)
    - "Turn About", unpublished manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Twenty-four Hours to Kill" High Spot Magazine, Aug. 1930 (Box 4)
    - "Tough Kid", manuscript (Box 4)
    - "Tourist Catalogue", ms. draft (Box 4)
    - "Two Hours to Go", manuscript fragments (Box 4)
    - "V is News" Short Stories, undated (Box 4a)
    - "The Voodoo Express", ms. draft, research material (Box 4a)
    - "The Voodoo Express" Argosy (photocopy), Oct. 10, 1931 (Box 4a)
    - "Vultures Over Europe", manuscript (Box 4a)
    - "Weird Stories", ms. draft (Box 4a)
    - "Where the Boys Are Marching", ms. draft (Box 4a)
    - "The Whip", unpublished manuscript (Box 4a)
    - "Who Killed Santy Claus?" (Theodore Roscoe/Henry W. Clune), ms. draft (Box 4a)
    - "Who Walks Like a Man", ms. drafts (Box 4a)
    - "Whom the Gods Destroy", unpublished manuscript (Box 4a)
    - "The Widow Wore Red", ms. drafts (Box 4a)
    - "Z is for Zombie", ms drafts (Box 4a)
    - "Zack the Giant Killer" Fight Stories, Aug. 1928 (Box 4a)
    - "Zombies Don't Talk", manuscript fragment (Box 4a)
  - Nonfiction (Box 4)
    - "About Your Religion", manuscript (Box 4a)
    - "The Abraham Lincoln Murder Case" The Reader's Digest, undated (Box 4a)
    - "Action at 31 Knots", manuscript (Box 4a)
    - Aircraft Radio Equipment, April 27, 1905 (Box 4a)
    - "American Energy Murder Mystery", research material, ms. drafts (Box 5)
    - "The Awful Truth About Fallout Shelters", manuscript (Box 5)
    - "Fast Ship for Harms Way", manuscript (Box 4)
    - "History for Dessert", manuscript (Box 5)
    - "Hugh Miller -- Arundel Is. Survival Story", ms. draft (Box 5)
    - "Musical Instruments Have Charms", manuscripts, photographs (Box 5)
    - Navy: History and Tradition, 1958; 1959; 24 cartoon books (Box 5)
    - Picture History of the U.S. Navy
      - Research materials, notes, ms. drafts (Box 5)
      - Ms. drafts, manuscripts, proofs (Box 6)
      - Photonegatives, photographs (Box 7)
      - Photonegatives, photographs, reviews (Box 8)
      - Oversize material (Oversize 1)
    - POW: the Fight Continues After the Battle (joint author), May 8, 1905 (Box 8)
    - "Report on the POW Report", ms. drafts, clippings (Box 8)
    - This Is Your Navy, 1950; manuscript, reviews; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - The Trent Affair, November, 1861, galley proof (Box 8)
    - True Tales of Bold Escapes, ms. drafts (Box 8)
    - United States Destroyer Operations in World War II, May 13, 1905 (Box 8)
    - United States Submarine Operations in World War II (working titles: "Submarine Force History", "Three Inches From Death")
      - Research material, ms. drafts (Box 9)
      - Ms. drafts, manuscript, photographs, reviews, front matter of Russian edition (photocopies) (Box 10)
      - [published edition? check...], May 18, 1965 (Box 10)
    - "WW III: Can We Ever Believe What We Read?", ms. draft, research material (Box 10)
  - Notebooks, 3 volumes (Box 10)
  - Reviews (by title) (Box 10)
  - Scripts (by title)
    - A-Bh (Box 10)
    - Bi-N (Box 11)
    - O-Z (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards (Oversize 1)
  - Financial material, 1952-1969; 1979,; undated (Box 12)
  - Printed materials
    - Books (Box 12, 13)
    - Books (oversize) (Oversize 1)
    - Clippings
      - About, 1953; 1992,; undated (Box 13)
      - Peripheral mention, 1991; undated (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous, 1871-1988; undated (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous (oversize), 1871-1988; undated (Oversize 1)
    - Publicity (Box 13)
    - Reviews (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks
    - "Navy Picture History, Book IV" (Box 13)
    - "Picture History, Book I, Part 1" (Box 13)
    - "Picture History, Book I, Part 3" (Box 13)
    - "Picture History, Book I, Part 3" (oversize) (Oversize 2)
    - "Picture History, Vol. II, Book I, Part 1, Spanish American War" (Box 13)
    - "Picture History, Vol. II, Book I, Part 1, Spanish American War" (oversize) (Oversize 2)
    - "Scrapbook" (Oversize 2)
    - "Some American History That May Not Be in the Schoolbooks" (Oversize 2)
    - "Your Navy" and "U.S. Submarines WW II" (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13)